OpenRLHF vs veRL: Ray Framework Deep Dive for Distributed RLHF (2025) | LLM Practical Experience Hub
LLM
LLM Hub
Home
Articles
Pricing
Knowledge Hub
Tools
NEW
About
Contact
Open main menu
Theme
Home
Articles
Pricing
Knowledge Hub
RAG Technology
Agent & Applications
Infrastructure
Reinforcement Learning
LLM Internals
Tools
NEW
Token Calculator
Prompt Library
Image Pricing
RAG Chunk Lab
All Calculators
About
Contact
0
%
Reinforcement Learning Hub
Hub
Advanced LLM training techniques
Explore
Reinforcement Learning Hub
Home
Knowledge Hub
Reinforcement Learning
OpenRLHF vs veRL: Ray Framework Deep Dive for Distributed RLHF (2025)
Home
Knowledge Hub
Reinforcement Learning Hub
OpenRLHF vs veRL: Ray Framework Deep Dive for Distributed RLHF (2025)
Technology
OpenRLHF vs veRL: Ray Framework Deep Dive for Distributed RLHF (2025)
Master distributed RLHF frameworks: Compare OpenRLHF and veRL architectures. Learn Ray Actors, GPU colocation, PPO implementation, and hybrid engine design for scalable reinforcement learning systems.
November 6, 2025
Qing Ke Ai
12
min read
#
OpenRLHF
#
veRL
#
RLHF
#
Ray framework
#
Reinforcement Learning
#
PPO
#
distributed training
#
GPU colocation
Share
Recommended next step
Token Calculator
Estimate rollout, evaluation, and inference token spend.
Prompt Library
Draft reward-model, evaluation, and critique prompts faster.
Complex Reinforcement Learning (RL) workloads, from RLHF to model distillation, depend on a sophisticated orchestration of computation, data communication, and process control across multiple models. A typical Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) setup, for instance, can involve up to five distinct modulesùActor, Rollout, Ref, Critic, and Rewardùeach performing specialized training, evaluation, or generation tasks.
Managing this complexity using a standard single-script, multi-process model launched with tools like
deepspeed
or
torchrun
presents significant limitations. Flexible task scheduling and dynamic resource allocation become intractable challenges.
This is where the
Ray framework
provides a powerful alternative for distributed RL.
Ray's remote asynchronous calls and Actor abstraction enable each module to operate as an independent execution unit. This decoupled architecture is ideal for scenarios demanding frequent collaboration between multiple models in a distributed RL training environment.
In this article, we will conduct a deep engineering analysis of two prominent RLHF frameworks,
veRL[1]
and
OpenRLHF[2]
. We will examine their features and architectural advantages, focusing on how they leverage a multi-Actor setup in the Ray framework to execute mixed training and inference tasks.
Our analysis will deconstruct these Reinforcement Learning frameworks from three key perspectives:
Module Responsibilities
: What role does each model play in PPO training, and what backends do they use?
Ray Resource Allocation
: How does Ray manage resources and implement GPU colocation?
Execution Flow
: How do data and control signals move through the distributed system?
This article contains numerous links to the source code, which we strongly encourage you to explore. Theoretical understanding is valuable, but diving into the code is the most effective way to build real-world expertise in distributed RL systems.
A Quick Primer on the Ray Framework
For those new to Ray, here is a summary of the core concepts required to understand this article.
How to Launch a Ray Cluster
While Ray offers APIs for multiple languages, the Python API is the most prevalent. Typically, a user starts a Python script and calls
ray.init()
, which automatically creates a local Ray cluster. The process running this script is known as the
driver
. Alternatively, a multi-node cluster can be started from the command line with
ray start
, allowing a script to connect to it.
Understanding Ray's Execution Logic
Under the hood, a Ray cluster is a pool of persistent worker processes. When a Python function or class is decorated with
@ray.remote
, it is transformed into a schedulable
Task
or
Actor
. It can then be invoked asynchronously using the
.remote()
method, which dispatches the Task[3] or Actor[4] to a worker process.
For the driver, these calls are non-blocking. To retrieve the results, one uses
ray.get()
to fetch the return value of the asynchronous operation.
Arguments and return values are serialized[5] into Ray
Objects
[6] and placed in the cluster's distributed object store. From Ray's perspective, the memory across all nodes functions as a unified object store. Developers pass object references, and Ray automatically fetches the data when
ray.get()
is called.
Here is a simple example demonstrating how Ray Actors can be composed:
import ray
ray.init()

@ray.remote
class ChildActor:
    def do_work(self):
        return "Work done by child"

@ray.remote
class ParentActor:
    def create_child(self):
        # Create a child actor remotely
        self.child_actor = ChildActor.remote()
    
    def get_work(self):
        # Remotely call the child and wait for the result
        return ray.get(self.child_actor.do_work.remote())

# Create the parent actor
parent_actor = ParentActor.remote()

# Remotely call create_child and wait for it to complete
ray.get(parent_actor.create_child.remote())

# Remotely call get_work and print the final result
print(ray.get(parent_actor.get_work.remote())) # Output: Work done by child
This demonstrates that one Ray Actor can create and call another. Note that standard Python inheritance cannot be used to inherit methods from another Actor class; the
@ray.remote
decorator should only be applied to the final class.
Resource Scheduling with Placement Groups
When creating a Ray Actor, you can specify the resources[7] it requires (e.g.,
num_cpus
,
num_gpus
). Ray's scheduler will then find a node with available resources to place the Actor. For more advanced scheduling, you can pre-define a
placement group
[8], which is a collection of resource
bundles
[9]. Actors can then be assigned to specific bundles, enabling both exclusive and shared resource patterns. This is the strategy adopted by both veRL and OpenRLHF for managing distributed RL workloads.
For instance, if an RLHF module uses a data parallelism (DP) degree of 4, one could create a placement group with 4 GPUs, define 4 bundles (each with 1 GPU), and then assign each DP worker to a unique bundle.
OpenRLHF Architecture: A Deep Dive into Distributed RL on Ray
From an engineering standpoint, OpenRLHF's code is clean and relatively straightforward. We will be examining the
v0.5.9.post1
release, focusing on its Ray-based PPO training implementation.
First, let's visualize the overall OpenRLHF architecture:
The diagram separates components on the driver process from those on remote Ray workers. The driver manages
PPORayActorGroup
[10] instances for each module (Actor, Critic, etc.). Each
Group
represents a complete logical model, while the remote workers are its data-parallel (DP) shards. For the Rollout module, the driver holds handles to one or more
LLMRayActor
s, each representing a vLLM engine.
Workers[12] within a group are created sequentially. The rank 0 worker (master) establishes the communication backend address[13], and subsequent workers connect to it. Communication is isolated between different groups, making each group's training process equivalent to a standard multi-process job.
Ray's abstractions elegantly hide low-level details, allowing each module to operate like an independent distributed task and simplifying the logic for complex, multi-model systems.
Training and Inference Backends: DeepSpeed and vLLM
Let's clarify the roles of each module in the PPO algorithm:
Actor
: A training module that updates its weights.
Critic
: A training and evaluation module that also updates weights.
Rollout
: A batch inference module for generating samples, synchronized with the Actor.
RM & Ref
: Evaluation-only modules performing forward passes.
For training, any engine like PyTorch DDP, Megatron, or DeepSpeed works. For inference, vLLM or SGLang are popular. OpenRLHF uses
DeepSpeed
for its training modules and
vLLM
for inference, which supports both data and tensor parallelism.
Ray Resource Scheduling and GPU Colocation
GPU Colocation
is the practice of having multiple Ray Actors share the same physical GPU. In OpenRLHF, this means placing shards from different modules (e.g., an Actor shard and a Critic shard) on the same GPU. They take turns using the hardware, often employing offloading strategies.
OpenRLHF supports three colocation modes:
colocate_actor_ref
,
colocate_critic_reward
, and
colocate_all_models
. A placement group is created, and workers for the colocated modules are assigned to its resource bundles. For example, to colocate five workers on one GPU, you could specify
num_gpus_per_actor=0.2
.
Modules that are not colocated get their own placement groups with exclusive GPU access.
The colocation of the
Actor
(DeepSpeed) and
Rollout
(vLLM) modules is particularly interesting. Since they must keep weights synchronized but cannot use NCCL on the same GPU, OpenRLHF uses
CUDA IPC
(Inter-Process Communication)[17]. After an
all_gather
within the Actor workers, the Actor's rank 0 worker broadcasts the complete weights to all Rollout instances.
Data and Control Flow in a Distributed Model
OpenRLHF lacks a central controller, meaning the overall execution logic is scattered. The process kicks off in the launch script[18] and passes control to the Actor group via
async_fit_actor_model
[19]. This triggers the
fit
method on all Actor workers, which is effectively
PPOTrainer.fit
.
From here, the control logic lives inside each Actor worker's trainer. Each Actor worker orchestrates data flow for its slice of the computation, communicating with a corresponding group of Ref, Critic, and RM workers[20] using a round-robin policy[21].
The core training loop is highly dispersed. A simplified representation is:
# In `PPOTrainer.fit`
for episode in range(num_episodes):
    # Generate experience samples
    sample_and_generate_rollout()
    make_exps()
    put_in_replay_buffer()

    # In `ActorPPOTrainer.ppo_train`
    for epoch in range(num_epochs):
        for exps in replay_buffer:
            train(exps) # This calls train_actor() and train_critic()
    
    clear_replay_buffer()
Crucially, all of this control logic is executed by the
Actor workers
. This design places a heavy computational and communication burden on the Actor workers, suggesting they could become a performance bottleneck in this distributed RL architecture.
veRL Architecture: A Centralized 'Single Controller' on Ray
The open-source code for veRL[22] features layers of abstractions, extracted from a mature internal codebase. Its standout feature is its
thorough decoupling of modules
, which makes extension easy. The framework also uses clever Python metaprogramming to allow a single Ray Actor to switch between multiple roles.
We'll examine version
v0.2.0.post2
, focusing on its Ray + FSDP implementation.
First, let's look at the veRL framework's composition:
Unlike OpenRLHF, veRL centralizes its main logic in a single Ray Actor[23] called a
"single controller."
This CPU-only controller acts as the system's brain, managing data flow, control flow, and resource initialization. It remotely creates and calls
WorkerDict
s, orchestrating all data transmission.
The most ingenious component is the
WorkerDict
. It's a base class for a Worker (a single model shard) designed to bind the public methods of
all
modules (Actor, Critic, etc.). This allows a
WorkerDict
instance to dynamically switch roles, becoming a universal, multi-personality Worker.
Layered on top is the
RayWorkerGroup
[24], which acquires resources from a placement group, configures a
WorkerDict
for a specific role, creates the
WorkerDict
instances, and dispatches tasks to them[25].
Training Backends and the Hybrid Engine Concept
In veRL, the training backend can be FSDP/HSDP or Megatron, while the inference module is vLLM. veRL also supports GPU colocation, but its primary strategy is to colocate
all
modules.
veRL heavily emphasizes its
Hybrid Engine
capability. Different modules share the same underlying
WorkerDict
data structure and resource group, allowing the
WorkerDict
to flexibly switch between different roles and engines. This is similar to the architecture of DeepSpeed-Chat[26].
A critical design choice in veRL is that the
Actor and Rollout modules share the same model weights in memory
[27]. This eliminates the need for explicit weight synchronization via CUDA IPC, unlike OpenRLHF. Since the Actor and Rollout components live in the same process, direct memory access replaces network communication. This is more memory-efficient but required extensive patching of vLLM.
Dynamic Workers and Resource Scheduling in Ray
The magic behind the dynamic
WorkerDict
starts with the
create_colocated_worker_cls
function. It dynamically creates a new class,
WorkerDict
, that instantiates
all
module classes (e.g.,
CriticWorker
) and stores them internally. Then, it binds the public methods of these module instances directly to the
WorkerDict
instance, adding a prefix like
critic_
.
A debugging session reveals the result:
(Pdb) p dir(self.workers[0])
['__init__', ...
'actor_rollout_compute_log_prob', 'actor_rollout_generate_sequences', ...
'critic_compute_values', 'critic_init_model', 'critic_update_critic', ... ]
The
WorkerDict
instance now has methods like
critic_init_model
that proxy calls to the internal
CriticWorker
instance[31].
This
WorkerDict
class is then passed to a
RayWorkerGroup
, which binds these prefixed methods to
itself
[32], adding powerful dispatch logic. When a method is called on the
RayWorkerGroup
(e.g.,
critic_wg.compute_values()
), it knows how to distribute data, execute the remote call on its
WorkerDict
Actors, and aggregate the results.
Centralized Data and Control Flow
Thanks to its single controller design, veRL's control logic is neatly centralized in
RayPPOTrainer
. The
init_workers
[37] method sets up the
WorkerDict
s, and the
fit
method contains the main PPO algorithm. This centralized approach improves code readability and extensibility compared to a distributed control model.
OpenRLHF vs. veRL: A Head-to-Head Architectural Comparison
To conclude, let's summarize the architectural trade-offs between these two Reinforcement Learning frameworks.
Module Design and Backend
Both frameworks deconstruct PPO into distinct modules. The key difference is veRL's flexible, multi-backend architecture, which allows for arbitrary combinations like FSDP + vLLM. This modularity is a powerful paradigm for advanced RLHF frameworks, though unifying APIs across backends is a significant challenge.
Ray Scheduling and Resource Management
The frameworks diverge significantly here. OpenRLHF launches a dedicated group of workers for each model and colocates them by rank. In contrast, veRL creates a single, universal
WorkerDict
that houses all models, naturally sharing resources.
OpenRLHF's approach is simpler, while veRL's 'symbiotic'
WorkerDict
is more efficient but required substantial engineering. Both
GPU Colocation
and a
Hybrid Engine
are essential features for maximizing hardware ROI in large-scale RL training.
Data Flow and Control Flow
The location of the control flow has a major impact on performance. OpenRLHF concentrates its control logic on the Actor workers, making them a potential system-wide bottleneck.
veRL's centralized
'single controller'
appears to be a more scalable design. It acts as a hub for control and data flow, leading to cleaner code from a readability and extensibility perspective.
One final observation is that both frameworks rely heavily on Ray's Object Store for data transfer. For large tensors, the overhead of serialization and memory copies can be a bottleneck. There is potential for optimization by replacing some transfers with direct NCCL or IPC communication, paving the way for even more efficient and scalable distributed AI systems.
Key Takeaways
ò OpenRLHF and veRL enhance scalability for complex RLHF workloads using the Ray framework.
ò Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) setups require managing multiple specialized modules efficiently.
ò Standard multi-process models face limitations; consider using advanced orchestration tools for better performance.
Further Reading
If you found this distributed RLHF architecture analysis helpful, explore these related resources:
Core RLHF Concepts:
Reinforcement Learning for LLMs: RLHF & DPO Explained (2025)
- Master the fundamentals of RLHF, DPO, and PPO algorithms that power both OpenRLHF and veRL frameworks.
Large-Scale Training:
Train 671B DeepSeek V3: RLHF Guide (10x Faster with GRPO)
- Learn how to train massive LLMs with reinforcement learning at scale, including Megatron setup and 1000+ GPU coordination strategies.
Pre-Training Foundation:
Supervised Fine-Tuning: A Guide to LLM Reasoning
- Understand the SFT pipeline that precedes RLHF, covering the complete DeepSeek R1 process from fine-tuning to knowledge distillation.
Related Topics:
Knowledge Hub: Reinforcement Learning
- Explore all RL-related articles, including RLHF techniques, DPO methods, and distributed training strategies for LLMs.
Further Reading
Recommended
Train 671B LLM with RL: Complete Guide
Scale RL training to 671B parameters using veRL framework with Megatron.
Read Article
Single vs Multi-Controller in veRL
Understand controller architectures inspired by Google's Pathways.
Read Article
30x Faster LLM RL Training: Checkpoint Engine
Optimize parameter sync in distributed RL with checkpoint-engine.
Read Article
Interactive Tool
Token Calculator
Estimate costs for large-scale distributed RL training.
Try Tool
Back to
Reinforcement Learning Hub
Hub
Explore More in
Reinforcement Learning Hub
This article is part of our Reinforcement Learning series. Discover more insights and practical guides.
Visit
Reinforcement Learning Hub
Related Articles in
Reinforcement Learning Hub
MoE Post-Training Guide: Load Balancing, Routing Replay, and Expert Parallelism
2026-03-25
A practical guide to MoE post-training, covering the tradeoff between load balancing and task quality, why RL becomes unstable when routing changes across engines or policy versions, and how to choose EP versus ETP in large-scale deployments.
Read More
WideSeek-R1: Width Scaling for Broad Information Seeking with Multi-Agent RL
2026-03-23
WideSeek-R1 reframes broad information seeking as an organizational problem, using a lead-agent-subagent MARL system to parallelize search and approach DeepSeek-R1-level performance with a 4B model.
Read More
Flexible Entropy Control in RLVR: Fixing Policy Entropy Collapse with Dynamic Clipping
2026-03-18
A practical guide to policy entropy collapse in RLVR and GRPO, covering why PPO clipping drives entropy decay and how dynamic clipping schedules restore exploration.
Read More
View All Articles in
Reinforcement Learning Hub
About This Article
Topic:
Technology
Difficulty:
Intermediate
Reading Time:
12
minutes
Last Updated:
November 6, 2025
This article is part of our comprehensive guide to Large Language Models and AI technologies. Stay updated with the latest developments in the AI field.
All Articles
Share this article to spread LLM knowledge
AI
Flying Elephant LLC
Sharing practical experience, hands-on techniques, and cognitive insights about Large Language Models. Focused on actionable methods and real project experience.
Navigation
Pricing
Compare Models
All Tools
About
Contact
Privacy Policy
Terms of Service
⌐
2026
Flying Elephant LLC. All rights reserved.
Empowering AI practitioners worldwide
